A Guide to the Francis Y. Joannes, Homes for the Newport News Shipbuilding and Dry Dock Company, Newport News, 1918
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Francis Y. Joannes, Homes for the Newport News Shipbuilding and Dry Dock Company, Architectural drawings, Newport News, 1918
Library of Virginia
42229
68 sheets of blueprint on linen; 137 x 53 cm. and smaller
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Elizabeth Broudy, Hampton, Virginia, 5 October 2005.
Biographical/Historical Information
Hilton Village, the first government-built housing development in the United States, was born out of a need for worker housing in the shipbuilding industry. During World War I, a severe lack of housing prevented companies such as the Newport News Shipbuilding and Dry Dock Company from filling the demand for American ships from European allies. Armed with a thorough economic study of the total cost, Newport News Shipbuilding and Dry Dock Company president, Homer L. Ferguson, went before the Emergency Fleet Corporation of the United States Shipping Board with a proposition. If the government would finance houses for shipyard workers, the shipyard would purchase the land, supervise the building, and rent or sell the houses to the workers under the terms agreed upon by the government. The government agreed to finance the $1.2 million project.
Influenced by the English garden cities movement, the development featured modest but well-built homes in the cottage style. Landscape architect Henry Vincent Hubbard and architect Francis Y. Joannes were responsible for the layout and design. Following the war, in 1921, the Shipping Board offered the village for sale at public auction. Henry E. Huntington, chairman of the shipyard, purchased Hilton Village and held it under the auspices of the Newport News Land Company. By 1922, the shipyard began to sell the homes to individuals. Due to the armistice, the full elaboration of the Hilton Village plan was never realized. In 1969, the village was added to the National Register of Historic Places, and in 1972 the Hilton Village Architectural Review Board was created by the General Assembly. The board reviews building permits and maintains a guide for homeowners.
Francis Yates Joannes (1876-1952) was a student of the Art Institute and Armour Institute of Chicago, a graduate of Cornell University, and received his professional training at the Ecole de Beaux-Arts in Paris (1904).
Scope and Content
This accession consists of the surviving record set of architectural drawings for the construction of Hilton Village in Newport News, Virginia. The drawings include elevations, floor plans, and details for thirty-five detatched or semi-detached residences and ten row house units. In addition, the set includes drawings for outhouses and a combination booster/railroad station. The latter was never constructed.
The verso of each sheet includes the transcribed signatures of representatives from the Shipbuilding Realty Corporation; Mellon-Stuart Co., general contractor; Noland-Clifford Co., Inc., plumbing sub- contractor; and Bluementhal-Kahn Electric Co., electrical sub-contractor.
Arrangement
Arranged by drawing number.
Contents List
- Sheet 3.1- House Type A 1, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.2- House Type A 2, Reverse of A 1, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.5- House Type B 1, House Type B 2, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.6- House Type B 3, House Type B4, Reverse of B1 B2, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.7- House Type B 5, House Type B 6, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.8- House Type BB 1, House Type BB 2, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.9- House Type C 1, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.10- House Type CC 1, House Type CC 2, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.12- House Type E 1, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.13- House Type E 2, Reverse of E 1, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.14- House Type EE 1, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.15- House Type F 1, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.16- House Type F 2, Reverse of F 1, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.17- House Type FF 1, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.18- House Type FF 2, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.19- House Type FF 3, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.20- House Type FF 4, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.21- House Type GG 1, House Type GG 2, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.22- House Type H 1, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.23- House Type H 2; Reverse of H 1, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.25- House Type J 1, House Type J 2, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.28- House Type K 1, House Type K 2, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.31- House Type L 1, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.32- House Type L2, Reverse of L 1, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.33- House Type M 1, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.34- House Type M 2, Reverse of M 1, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.5- House Type MM 1, House Type MM 2, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.36- Outhouses, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.37- Material Changes for Exterior of Houses, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.38- Booster and Railroad Station, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.39- Booster and Railroad Station, 1918 (Folder 1)
- Sheet 3.361- Elevations and Foundation Plans, Row 1, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.362- 1st and 2nd Floor Plans, Row 1, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.363- Row 1 Elevations, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.371- Row 2, Elevations and Foundation Plans, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.372- 1st and 2nd Floor Plan, Row 2, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.373- Row 2, Elevations, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.381- Row 3-6, Foundation Plans, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.382- Rows 3 & 6, 1st and 2nd Floor Plans, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.383- Row 3-6, Elevations, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.391- Row 4, Elevations and Foundation Plans, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.392- Row 4, 1st and 2nd Floor Plans, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.393- Row 4, Elevations, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.401- Row 5, Elevations and Foundation Plans, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.402- Row 5, 1st and 2nd Floor Plans, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.403- Row 5, Elevations, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.421- Row 7, Elevations and Foundation Plans, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.422- Row 7, 1st and 2nd Floor Plans, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.423- Row 7, Elevations, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.431- Row 8, Plan and Elevations, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.441- Row 8, Elevations and Foundation Plans, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.442- Row 9, 1st and 2nd Floor Plans, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.443- Row 9, Elevations, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.471- Row 12, Foundation Plans, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.472- Row 12, 1st Floor Plans, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.473- Row 12, 2nd Floor Plans, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.474- Row 12, Elevations, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.475- Row 12, Elevations, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.481- Row 13, Foundation Plans, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.482- Row 13, 1st Floor Plans, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.483- Row 13, 2nd Floor Plans, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.484- Row 13, Elevations, 1918 (Folder 2)
- Sheet 3.485- Row 13, Elevations, 1918 (Folder 2)